<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-04-18T17:43:03-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">MALOLEY.ME</title><subtitle>Just a place to share my thoughts with others. Property and copyright belongs to Richard Maloley II. Please contact me for permission to use my content and I will do the same. Thanks :-).</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Vulnerability Management 101</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/18/vulnerability-management-101.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vulnerability Management 101" /><published>2022-04-18T01:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-18T01:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/04/18/vulnerability-management-101</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/18/vulnerability-management-101.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="../../../files/vulnerability-management-framework.png" alt="Vulnerability Management Framework" /></p>

<p>Recently a client of mine had another firm perform an external vulnerability scan to satisfy a cyber insurance requirement. This firm identified several systems that either utilized, or could use, TLS 1.0 and 1.1 for secure communications. While this is rated as a “medium” vulnerability it should still be resolved, especially as it was an external vulnerability.</p>

<p>Today I’m going to use that prompt to briefly discuss the basics of Vulnerability Management and walk through an example where I mitigate the identified vulnerabilities on one of my assets.</p>

<p>Vulnerability Management quite simply put is a framework that you follow to find and remediate vulnerabilities within your organization. While this framework is most commonly tied to vulnerability scans and assessments it can be utilized for other types of risks such as physical.</p>

<p>The framework I advocate for is as follows: <strong>Scan</strong> your assets. <strong>Identify</strong> the vulnerability. <strong>Research</strong> solutions to identified vulnerabilities. <strong>Remediate</strong> the vulnerability. <strong>Document</strong> the remediation or other outcomes (for example if you accept the risk of the vulnerability and do not remediate it.) Then scan again to <em>continue the process</em>.</p>

<p>The Vulnerability Management process should be a part of your larger Security Program within the organization. It is not a one-time process but meant to be continuous. Parts or all of this process can be owned within the organization or outsourced to trusted partners.</p>

<p>Lets go ahead and walk through this process using a real-world example.</p>

<p>Our first step is to scan our environment with a vulnerability scanner. Having done so I can see that there are indeed vulnerabilities that should be mitigated. Please note that this guide is only going to discuss the remediation of a single vulnerability.</p>

<p><img src="../../../files/vulnerability-management-example-01.png" alt="Example vulnerabilities" /></p>

<p>TLS 1.0 and 1.1 are older versions of TLS that have been deprecated<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote">1</a></sup>. Services and applications should utilize TLS 1.2 or 1.3 instead. TLS 1.2 has been recommended since 2008 and it is now 2022.</p>

<p>Now that we have identified the vulnerabilities we need to do some research. What asset(s) is affected by this vulnerability? What application or service is this vulnerability affecting? Is there a known remediation for this vulnerability for this application or service?</p>

<p>First we need to identify the assets that are affected by this vulnerability. In my case I did a scan of my homelab network. From the vulnerability scanner report I can clearly identify the affected assets.</p>

<p><img src="../../../files/vulnerability-management-example-02.png" alt="Example vulnerabilities" /></p>

<p>From the report my affected assets are 192.168.86.203 and 192.168.86.205. I can also see that the application or service is likely an email server.</p>

<p>Now I can refer to my asset database, also known as a CMDB<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote">2</a></sup> (configuration management database), to identify more information on these assets. From my CMDB I know that these two assets are Ubuntu servers. As these are Ubuntu servers it is likely that the mail server is Postfix.</p>

<p>It could be that I simply need to update the version of Postfix that is installed. That is not the case for this asset. Further research on the Postfix website shows that there is a method for enabling and disabling protocols in the configuration<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote">3</a></sup> file.</p>

<p>We have concluded the research step of this process. We have a remediation plan: Update the Postfix configuration file to enable TLS 1.2 and disable the depreciated protocol version. At this point we can move to the remediation step. Depending on your organization this is where Change Management processes may also come into play. As this is my homelab I will simply make the appropriate changes.</p>

<p><em>Don’t forget to backup the /etc/postfix/main.cf configuration file!</em></p>

<p>My default configuration file did not specify the TLS parameters so we’ll need to add them. I used the following lines - this works for my homelab - be sure to do thorough research before performing this step in your organization.</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">smtp_tls_mandatory_protocols=!SSLv2, !SSLv3, !TLSv1, !TLSv1.1</code><br />
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">smtpd_tls_mandatory_protocols=!SSLv2, !SSLv3, !TLSv1, !TLSv1.1</code><br />
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">smtp_tls_protocols=!SSLv2, !SSLv3, !TLSv1, !TLSv1.1</code><br />
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">smtpd_tls_protocols=!SSLv2, !SSLv3, !TLSv1, !TLSv1.1</code></p>

<p>After updating the configuration file the Postfix service will need to be restarted. Be aware of the potential outage when scheduling this kind of work in your own organization.</p>

<p>At this point the vulnerability should be resolved. There should also be a trove of documentation ranging from the original scanning reports to your remediation plan. How will we know? We go back to the beginning of the process and scan again to validate that our remediation plan was successful.</p>

<p><img src="../../../files/vulnerability-management-example-03.png" alt="Example vulnerabilities" /></p>

<p>We have now successfully remediated this vulnerability.</p>

<p>While this example was specifically geared towards resolving the specific vulnerability with Postfix on an Ubuntu server asset, the vulnerability management framework presented can be applied to any organization and team tasked with identifying and remediating vulnerabilities within the organization.</p>

<hr />

<p>Footnotes:</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>See <a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-tls-oldversions-deprecate-00">https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-tls-oldversions-deprecate-00</a> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>See <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Configuration_management_database">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Configuration_management_database</a> <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>See <a href="https://www.postfix.org/postconf.5.html#smtpd_tls_mandatory_protocols">https://www.postfix.org/postconf.5.html#smtpd_tls_mandatory_protocols</a> <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="security" /><category term="vulnerabilities" /><category term="framework" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Open Letter to Chief Eric Winstrom</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/14/an-open-letter-to-chief-eric-winstrom.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Open Letter to Chief Eric Winstrom" /><published>2022-04-14T01:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-14T01:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/04/14/an-open-letter-to-chief-eric-winstrom</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/14/an-open-letter-to-chief-eric-winstrom.html"><![CDATA[<p>April 14, 2022</p>

<p>Chief Eric Winstrom<br />
1 Monroe Center St NW<br />
Grand Rapids, MI 49503</p>

<p>Chief Winstrom,</p>

<p>I am a fellow citizen of Michigan who works in, pays taxes to, and enjoys the City of Grand Rapids. As a taxpayer I am exercising my right to convey to you my thoughts on the Patrick Lyoya crisis. It is, indeed, a crisis.</p>

<p>I try to see the good in all people. I live my life assuming positive intent in all interactions until proven otherwise. Chief I believe that you are sincere in your statements that you wish to be transparent and that you wish to reform the police department. As a taxpayer I intend to hold you accountable to those statements.</p>

<p>As a taxpayer I do not wish my tax monies to be spent on the salary or defense of the Officer involved in this crisis. The Officer violated at least one, if not multiple, rules and regulations of the GRPD. The video clearly shows that the Officer assaulted a Citizen during an alleged traffic violation. <a href="https://public.powerdms.com/GRANDRAPIDS/documents/99698">City Rules and Regulations Page 2 Paragraph 8</a></p>

<p>The Officer violated at least one, if not multiple, rules and regulations regarding traffic enforcement as documented in GRPD policy. Specifically the Officer failed to properly greet the driver and explain the reason for the stop, and the Officer did not treat the subject with respect or courtesy. <a href="https://public.powerdms.com/GRANDRAPIDS/documents/269466">Manual of Procedures - Traffic Enforcement - 3b - Conduct</a></p>

<p>The Officer violated policy 11.1 of the Manual of Conduct by assaulting a citizen of Grand Rapids who was not acting aggressively towards the Officer. The Officer violated policy 18.1 A where their actions have brought disrepute into the Department.  <a href="https://public.powerdms.com/GRANDRAPIDS/documents/88407">Manual of Conduct - Policy 18.1A</a></p>

<p>The actions of your Officer and your Department are detrimental and the opposite of both the Mission Statement and the Vision Statement of the Department.</p>

<p>“Protect life and property, prevent crime, and ensure all people feel safe and
are safe at all times throughout our community.” <a href="https://public.powerdms.com/GRANDRAPIDS/documents/88410">GRPD Mission Statement</a></p>

<p>“In partnership with our community, we will become the safest mid-sized city
and most trusted police department in the United States.” <a href="https://public.powerdms.com/GRANDRAPIDS/documents/88410">GRPD Vision Statement</a></p>

<p>The actions of the Officer and the Department do not uphold the Mission or Vision and therefore the Officer and the Department have failed in both the Mission and the Vision. The actions have instead taken life, made the community unsafe, and has reduced the trust even further.</p>

<p>The Officer broke the first Value of the Department by assaulting a fellow citizen and turning a safe situation into an unsafe situation which resulted in the death of a fellow citizen. This is unacceptable. <a href="https://public.powerdms.com/GRANDRAPIDS/documents/88410">“Service –Through compassion, empathy and courage, we are driven to
meet the public safety needs of our community”</a></p>

<p>For all the attested reasons, and as the video evidence has clearly shown, the Officer is not fit for duty as a law enforcement officer in this or any jurisdiction. I call on you to relieve the Officer of all duties for violating department policy and assaulting a Citizen. I call on you to exercise the values of Integrity and Accountability as reflected in GRPD policy.</p>

<p>For the community to heal - to truly heal - there must be integrity, accountability, and trust. This requires the Department to make different choices and to earn back that trust by having integrity and being accountable to the Citizens of this great city. It will also require a change in the culture of the Department. Culture is the embodiment of beliefs, values, and behaviors of an organization. The exhibited behaviors betray the Mission and Values. Thus to enable healing you, as the leader, must change the culture of the Department that you lead.</p>

<p>You cannot change the past. You can make a different choice today. A better choice today can lead to an even better tomorrow.</p>

<p>Sincerely,</p>

<p>Richard Maloley II</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="police" /><category term="layoya" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[April 14, 2022]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Patrick Lyoya</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/13/on-patrick-lyoya.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Patrick Lyoya" /><published>2022-04-13T01:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-13T01:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/04/13/on-patrick-lyoya</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/13/on-patrick-lyoya.html"><![CDATA[<p>On April 4, 2022, a tragedy happened. Another unarmed person, a young person of color, a young man with a full life ahead of him, was killed by an Officer with the Grand Rapids Police Department. After much public outcry and pressure the Chief of Police Eric Winstrom agreed to share the videos of the tragedy. A news conference and presentation happened on April 13, 2022. After watching the video and taking time for reflection I wrote the words below.</p>

<hr />
<hr />
<hr />

<p>Having watched the GRPD video of the terrible event: Not reasonable and not justified.</p>

<p>GRPD failed at 2:48 into the video when the Officer laid his hands on Mr. Lyoya. At this point the Officer escalated and lost control of the situation. From there on in the entire death could have been prevented.</p>

<p>It is not reasonable in this scenario to assault a citizen for walking away. At this point in the video the Officer has full video of the citizen and the citizen’s vehicle for impound, in addition to a passenger who can be questioned. Mr. Lyoya could have been sought after through regular investigatory channels and detained safely in the future.</p>

<p>There is no justification for an officer to pursue a citizen over a non-violent minor alleged traffic violation.</p>

<p>It is clear that there is a cultural and training issue in the GRPD that must be fixed. These actions are indicative of a culture of “us versus them” meaning that the Officer is not equal to the Citizen. There can be no trust in a culture like this. Secondly the training (if this then that) appears to instruct in escalation as opposed to deescalation. That will almost always make the situation worse.</p>

<p>Finally it is clear to me that GRPD Officers in the field must be issued different equipment. The cameras must be attached with a stronger device and they must be configured in such a way that it requires two hands and five seconds of direct interaction to disable. It is also time to require the use of less-lethal ammunition in the primary duty magazine. The use of a less-lethal ammunition may have saved Mr. Lyoya’s life.</p>

<p>I’m angry. I’m sad. More-so I am so disappointed in both the GRPD and the City Commissioners. I’m heartbroken that we perpetuate these broken systems that consistently lead to these terrible outcomes.</p>

<p>My prayers are with the family and the city.</p>

<p>The full video can be accessed here. It is graphic: <a href="https://www.woodtv.com/news/grand-rapids/grand-rapids-police-department-patrick-lyoya-shooting-video-released/">Press Conference and Videos</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="police" /><category term="civil" /><category term="rights" /><category term="protest" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On April 4, 2022, a tragedy happened. Another unarmed person, a young person of color, a young man with a full life ahead of him, was killed by an Officer with the Grand Rapids Police Department. After much public outcry and pressure the Chief of Police Eric Winstrom agreed to share the videos of the tragedy. A news conference and presentation happened on April 13, 2022. After watching the video and taking time for reflection I wrote the words below.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Site and Musings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/08/new-site-and-musings.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Site and Musings" /><published>2022-04-08T01:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-08T01:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/04/08/new-site-and-musings</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/08/new-site-and-musings.html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to the new and upgraded website. I decided to move to a static site generator created site.</p>

<p>More later.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="updates" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have a new site.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Leadership Words and Quotes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/08/leadership-words-and-quotes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Leadership Words and Quotes" /><published>2021-02-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/08/leadership-words-and-quotes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/08/leadership-words-and-quotes.html"><![CDATA[<p>This entry will hold a running list of words and quotes that I believe contribute to effective leadership.</p>

<p>If you mess up, ‘fess up.</p>

<p>Perfect is the enemy of good.</p>

<p>Sometimes the leader is simply the person who showed up.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="leadership" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This entry will hold a running list of words and quotes that I believe contribute to effective leadership.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Demystifying Zero Trust</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/18/zero-trust.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Demystifying Zero Trust" /><published>2021-01-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/18/zero-trust</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/18/zero-trust.html"><![CDATA[<p>Zero Trust isn’t a real thing. I’ll more another day.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="zero" /><category term="trust" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Zero Trust isn’t a real thing. I’ll more another day.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The One Change to Make</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/13/the-one-change-to-make.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The One Change to Make" /><published>2021-01-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/13/the-one-change-to-make</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/13/the-one-change-to-make.html"><![CDATA[<p>It is 2021 and we all have our New Year’s Resolutions. Today I ask you to make one easy change to better protect your digital self: Move from passwords to passphrases.</p>

<p><img src="https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/password_strength.png" alt="XKCD" />
Source: https://xkcd.com/936/</p>

<p>Please switch to using passphrases in systems, websites, and applications that you can. A passphrase is:</p>

<p>Easier to dream up and easier to recall.
Complex by default.
Difficult to duplicate.
Near impossible to guess by an adversary.
Use a passphrase. When you see password think passphrase.</p>

<p>Your local computer security guru will thank you.</p>

<p>-Richard</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="security" /><category term="password" /><category term="passphrase" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It is 2021 and we all have our New Year’s Resolutions. Today I ask you to make one easy change to better protect your digital self: Move from passwords to passphrases.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Year of Linux</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/10/the-year-of-linux.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Year of Linux" /><published>2021-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/10/the-year-of-linux</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/10/the-year-of-linux.html"><![CDATA[<p>I have long been a proponent if the Linux and opensource philosophy. I’ve <a href="https://www.howtoforge.com/openldap-samba-domain-controller-ubuntu7.10">contributed to the community</a>. I sincerely believe that the opensource model is the democratic ideal of sharing knowledge. Knowledge should be free and easily accessible to all. To that end this year I’ve made a personal decision to use Linux full-time in my personal capacity.</p>

<p>All of us have used Linux and associated technologies in our everyday lives. Every Android phone and Chromebook laptop runs Linux. Web services are built on it. When you think of modern computing systems you naturally think of Microsoft and Apple as being the most prevalent. I, however, believe that Linux and the opensource ecosystem is not only viable but very usable for most people.</p>

<p>I’ve picked up a System76 Lemur Pro laptop for this journey. It runs PopOS which is a derivative of Ubuntu which is a further derivative of Debian. After two full days of use I am very happy with the choice. I both create and consume content and thus far I have not been hampered in my efforts.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="linux" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have long been a proponent if the Linux and opensource philosophy. I’ve contributed to the community. I sincerely believe that the opensource model is the democratic ideal of sharing knowledge. Knowledge should be free and easily accessible to all. To that end this year I’ve made a personal decision to use Linux full-time in my personal capacity.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Privacy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/on-privacy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Privacy" /><published>2020-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/on-privacy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/on-privacy.html"><![CDATA[<p>“Our idea of privacy is a continuous illusion that we create and destroy day in and day out.”</p>

<p>What is privacy? A common definition is “the state or condition of being free from being observed or disturbed by other people.” Obviously that definition is wholly inadequate for modern society. I’d even argue that it has never been applicable to us as a people.</p>

<p>Phonebook</p>

<p>Image Source: https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d3/Telefonbog_ubt-1.JPG</p>

<p>Do you remember those days? Every year every household serviced by a telephone provider (and often those without telephone service) would receive a book. Inside this book was the full name, address, and phone number for everyone in your area code. Back then you had to pay extra to be un-listed.</p>

<p>Lets identify some pieces of data that we would consider private.</p>

<p>Name
Address
Phone Number
Email Address
Home Address
Employer
Social Security Number
Birthday
Bank account(s)
Credit account(s)
Property tax information
Home internet address
Emails
Text messages
Residence history
Voter registration information
Vacation plans
Child school information
There is a lot of data that I would classify as private in that list. I want you to do a quick exercise: Who has these various bits of data?</p>

<p>Your name, address, phone number, email address, birthday, and social security number have been shared with your employer, your banks, your creditors, and the credit reporting agencies. The credit reporting agencies have your entire residence history as that is one way to prove you are who you are. Given your name, birthday, and zip code anyone can look up your voter registration information. With your address anyone can see your property tax information and history. Your phone provider will absolutely give the state a copy of your text messages and your email provider likely will too. Your ISP keeps a record of which internet addresses have been assigned to your residence at any given time for a period of at least a year. How many companies have your credit card data saved? Do you even know?</p>

<p>What else could we consider private data? Would you consider photos of your children to be private? Perhaps their names or their school? What about when you are going to go on vacation? Would you consider your destination and departure/arrival data to be private? I would but it seems like a lot of people do not based on social media posts.</p>

<p>Do you have more or less privacy today? My answer is Yes.</p>

<p>Yes, we can have more privacy today. Yes, we could have had more privacy in 1984. Privacy at the end of the day, to an extent, is what you want it to be.</p>

<p>Privacy is a dial that is paired with a balance beam hovering in the event horizon of a black hole. There are individual actions that we can all take to better control our private data. However to fully participate in our society we must give up some of that privacy.</p>

<p>The point of this post isn’t to correct you or to fix the system. The point is to simply make you aware that there are things both in and out of your control and you simply need to be aware of them.</p>

<p>Think of all the places where you hand someone your official state identification. Or your credit card. Think of the times you ordered takeout and provided your name, phone number, and credit card data.</p>

<p>Think your private data will stay private? I should add that I’ve audited organizations and I have found electronic copies of birth certificates, identification cards, tax records, financial authorization forms, and more! Consider how many people have handled this data. I’m sure most people were honest and ethical but how many are not?</p>

<p>Now go through an exercise of your daily life. You hop onto public transportation wearing a shirt with your employers name on the breast. You wear your employee identification badge. You take a selfie in the morning and post it on Facebook or Instagram. You post when you leave for work and what you are doing after work. Every interaction you have where you give out your private data you are entrusting the other entity to protect that data. Yet we know from our own experience that this doesn’t always work out the way we want it to.</p>

<p>I’m a very private individual, yet you wouldn’t know it by my web presence. I intentionally make parts of my life not-private because this is my business. I work with people to advise them on being better aware of security considerations.</p>

<p>My goal here isn’t to scare you into being a hermit (however a traditional hermit lifestyle is a valid method of maintaining privacy). Instead my goal is to simply help you to open your eyes and be more aware of your daily interactions. I aim to give you knowledge and tools to help you stay more secure as you navigate this ever interconnected world that we find ourselves in.</p>

<p>Our idea of privacy is a continuous illusion that we create and destroy day in and day out. How will you control your privacy tomorrow?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="privacy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“Our idea of privacy is a continuous illusion that we create and destroy day in and day out.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Password Best Practices</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/27/password-best-practices.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Password Best Practices" /><published>2020-11-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-11-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/27/password-best-practices</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/27/password-best-practices.html"><![CDATA[<p>Passwords. We all hate them. There are only a few things in life that I hate. Passwords are amongst those things. Truth be told it isn’t the function that I hate but the arcane implementations and policies that lead us to bad passwords. That is a fundamental truth. I say we just admit to that truth and move on to some practical advice. The goal for this musing is to introduce some best practices that anyone can follow to improve their use of passwords immediately.</p>

<p>There are four main topics that this document addresses:</p>

<p>Creating better passwords.
Managing your passwords.
Better than passwords.
Take it to the next level.
Creating Better Passwords
There are several rules that make a password good. A good password:</p>

<p>Is something that you know and no one else knows
Is something that you can remember
Is something that cannot be easily guessed
OK those are some obvious basic ideas of what a good password is. What makes a password bad? There are a few rules to follow that prevent bad passwords. Don’t:</p>

<p>Use simple dictionary words such as “apple” or “cat”
Use the word “password” or any variation
Use words that convey seasons or months
Use your company name
Capitalize only the first letter
Put special characters (!*$%) only at the end
What steps can you take to make better passwords then?</p>

<p>Ignore grammar and spelling
Use multiple words
Do the opposite of what human nature dictates
Confused yet? That is OK. Let me give you some practical examples.</p>

<p>Bad Password: Password1234
Bad Password: March2020
Bad Password: P@ssw0rd1234
OK Password: cAtdog1234
OK Password: 1dOgcat234
Better Password: work@CatDog20201127!
Better Password: gmail@CatDog20201127!
Did you notice something about the “Better” password examples? Yes, I reused a portion of the password but in the end I had two unique passwords. This is an example of a method of creating both a good and unique password for your various accounts. The first step is to define a strong password. Then apply a unique pre-or-post-fix to make the password unique for each service.</p>

<p>Managing Your Passwords
Managing your passwords is easier than you may think. I make two key recommendations in this topic.</p>

<p>Follow the earlier principle to design a unique but memorable password for each service.
Use a password manager.
In the first case your password, and the associated service(s), should help you remember the account and password. They both work together to autheticate you to the service. For example if you are logging in to GMAIL then your password would be GMAIL + password.</p>

<p>In the second case you should use some sort of password manager. This gives you the ability to generate random passwords that you never have to remember. So long as you have access to the password manager then you’ll be able to gain access to your known passwords.</p>

<p>For password managers I recommend using a program that you can access across all of your devices. Personally I use LastPass. No, I don’t make money from recommending the service. Why do I like this service?</p>

<p>I only need to remember one password to get access to all of my accounts.
I can use the program on all of my computers and phones.
It can autofill the username and password on most websites.
At the end of the day you should device a system that works for you. It starts with creating a better password then managing your passwords in a manner that makes sense for you.</p>

<p>Better Than Passwords
When you think of the word “password” your mind instantly thinks of a single word. Then your knowledge kicks in and you realize that you need more than just a simple word and so you add character substitutions, capitalization, and special characters at the end of the word. It takes you an awful lot of effort to create that password. Is it strong enough you hope? Will I remember it you ask? Which service was this for again?</p>

<p>Passwords suck. Passphrases, however, rule.</p>

<p>My name is Richard Maloley II</p>

<p>A passphrase is a phrase that you use for a password instead of a traditional password. The above phrase works as a strong and complex password. It consists of 31 characters. It has capital letters. It has special characters. It is not a single word password. This is a good password and it is simple to remember. Even better is that if spoken it is nearly impossible for an attacker to figure out how to use this password.</p>

<p>Instead of passwords start thinking of passphrases. This is my Facebook password. This is my work email password. A passphrase is easier to create and easier to remember.</p>

<p>Take It To The Next Level
You’ve learned what makes a password bad. You’ve learned what makes a password good. You’ve learned about ways to manage your password so that you can easily remember them and keep them sure. You’ve also learned that instead of traditional passwords the use of a passphrase is easier and stronger. Now we’ll go one step further - multifactor authentication.</p>

<p>Multifactor authentication simply means that you perform an additional action above and beyond entering your username and password. You’ve encountered this often and for some time now though you may not have known what this is. For example when you log into your banking website the bank will text you a code. This is a version of multifactor authentication.</p>

<p>There are numerous version or types of factors for multifactor authentication. This document isn’t design to get into all of the different factors. Instead my writing is simply meant to inform you of the option and to convince you to turn it on.</p>

<p>The vast majority if your common services will have the option to enable multifactor authentication. You should always enable this option. Do this on your banking website. Do this on your Facebook/Twitter/Parler/Instagram and other social media. Do this on your email.</p>

<p>The default option, likely a text to your phone, is fine for your use case. There may be other options available. Personally I am a fan of hardware tokens. I utilize a YubiKey hardware token to secure many of my accounts.</p>

<p>At this point you should be armed with the knowledge and capabilities to create and manage better passwords (or passphrases) to secure your online accounts. Good luck and practice safe cyber habits.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="security" /><category term="password" /><category term="passphrase" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Passwords. We all hate them. There are only a few things in life that I hate. Passwords are amongst those things. Truth be told it isn’t the function that I hate but the arcane implementations and policies that lead us to bad passwords. That is a fundamental truth. I say we just admit to that truth and move on to some practical advice. The goal for this musing is to introduce some best practices that anyone can follow to improve their use of passwords immediately.]]></summary></entry></feed>